David E. Lilienthal Papers, 1900-1981 (bulk 1950-1981 ): Inventory
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
David E. Lilienthal Papers
1900-1981
1950-1981
MC148
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Special Collections. Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. Public Policy Papers. 65 Olden Street Princeton, New Jersey 08540 USA
278.9 linear feet 632 boxes and 2 oversize folders
Lilienthal, David Eli, 1899-1981.
David Lilienthal served on the Wisconsin Public Service Commission (1923-1932), as a member of the board of directors (1933-1941) and then chairman (1941-1946) of the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA), as first chairman (1946-1950) of the Atomic Energy Commission, and, later, in private business as an industrial consultant and chairman (1955) of the Development and Resources Corporation, which was involved with the Khuzestan Program in Iran. This collection consists of the papers of Lilienthal spanning his entire career, including correspondence, reports, articles, speeches, and printed matter.
1931 Wisconsin Railroad Commission
1931-1932 Wisconsin Public Service Commission, Member Commissioner
1933-1946 Tennessee Valley Authority Member, Board of Directors, 1933-1940 Director and Chairman, 1941-1946
1946 United States Department of State, Board of Consultants on the International Control of Atomic Energy, Chairman
1946-1950 U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, Chairman
Publications by Lilienthal: TVA, Democray on the March (New York: Harper & Brothers, 1944), This I Do Believe (New York: Harper, 1949), Big Business, A New Era (New York: Harper, 1953), Change, Hope, and the Bomb (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1963), The Journals of David E. Lilienthal, vols. I-VII. (New York: Harper, 1964-1983), and Atomic Energy, A New Start (New York: Harper & Row, 1980)
This collection consists of the papers of Lilienthal spanning his entire career. Included are correspondence, reports, articles, speeches, and printed matter relating to his positions with the Wisconsin Public Service Commission (1923-1932), as a member of the board of directors (1933-1941) and then chairman (1941-1946) of the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA), as first chairman (1946-1950) of the Atomic Energy Commission, and, later, in private business as an industrial consultant and chairman (1955) of the Development and Resources Corporation, which was involved with the Khuzestan Program in Iran. Also present are manuscripts for six works, including TVA, Democracy on the March (1944), Big Business, A New Era (1953), Atomic Energy, A New Start (1980), and the published Journals of David E. Lilienthal, Vols. I-VII, 1939-1981 (1964-1983), as well as his personal, unpublished, manuscript journals (1915-1981).
Other personal papers include documents, early correspondence (1917-1923) with his future wife, Helen Lamb, and other family members, appointment books, scrapbooks, film and tape recordings, photographs, and memorabilia.
The materials in this collection may have been put in this order by Lilienthal or his administrative staff before transfer to Princeton, and further arrangement may have been done by an archivist at Princeton but no information is available regarding the extent to which an archivist was involved in the current arrangement. In 2019 a number of materials after series 22 were rehoused and merged with corresponding series into series 8, 10-13, and 25. Other series that are are broken up in in two, including speeches and correspondence, are left intact.
LINKED DIGITAL CONTENT NOTE: Please note that some previously linked digital content is temporarily unavailable while the data is being migrated from an outdated access service. If you would like to access this content, please send a request to mudd@princeton.libanswers.com.
Collection is open for research use.
Access to audiovisual material in this collection follows the Mudd Manuscript Library policy for preservation and access to audiovisual materials.
The original collection was a gift from David E. Lilienthal in 1965. Several additions to the collection were received over the next two decades, the last one for which documentation exists was in July 1987. Amendments to the original 1965 Deed of Gift allow access to previously restricted materials.
No information about appraisal is available for this collection>
Development and Resources Corporation.; Public Service Commission of Wisconsin.; Railroad Commission of Wisconsin.; Tennessee Valley Authority.; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; United States. -- Atomic Energy Act of 1946.; United States. -- Atomic Energy Act of 1954.; Big business -- United States -- 20th century.; Chemical industries -- United States -- 20th century.; Dams -- Iran -- 20th century.; Dams -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Economic development projects -- Iran -- Khuzestan -- 20th century.; Economic development projects -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Flood control -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Flood dams and reservoirs -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Industries -- Power supply -- 20th century.; Mineral industries -- United States -- 20th century.; Natural resources -- Developing countries -- 20th century.; Nuclear energy -- United States.; Nuclear industry -- United States.; Nuclear nonproliferation.; Power resources -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Public utilities -- Wisconsin.; Railroads and state -- United States -- 20th century.; Regional planning -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Rural development -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Rural electrification -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; Water resources development -- Tennessee -- 20th century.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects -- United States.; Industries -- Power supply -- United States -- 20th century.; Khuzestan (Iran) -- Economic conditions -- 20th century.; Tennessee -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; Audio tapes.; Autobiographies.; Correspondence.; Journals.; Manuscripts.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Lawyers -- United States -- 20th century.; Public officers -- United States -- 20th century.; American history/20th century; American politics and government; Cold War; Economic history; International organizations
- Series 1: Articles, books, and Lecture Notes by David E. Lilienthal, 1918-1952; 16 boxes
  Series 1: Articles, books, and lecture notes includes articles and books written by Lilienthal from 1918-1949 and lecture notes from Lilienthal's time at law school.
  The materials in this series are arranged in chronological order.
  - 1918, portion of 1 box
  - 1922, 2 boxes (1 partial)
    - (1 of 2), 1922; portion of 1 box
    - (2 of 2), 1922; 1 box
  - 1923-1926, 1 box
  - 1927-1933, 1 box
  - 1935-1943, 1 box
  - 1944, 6 boxes
    - (1 of 6), 1944; 1 box
      Includes: TVA - Democracy On The March, Harper & Brothers, 1944. [Filed in Boxes 6-11.1]
    - (2 of 6), 1944; 1 box
    - (3 of 6), 1944; 1 box
    - (4 of 6), 1944; 1 box
    - (5 of 6), 1944; 1 box
    - (6 of 6), 1944; 1 box
  - 1945-1946, 1 box
  - 1947-1948, 1 box
  - 1949, 1947-1952; 3 boxes
    - (1 of 3), 1949; 1 box
    - (2 of 3), 1949; 1 box
      Includes: This I Do Believe, Harper & Brothers, 1949. [Filed in Boxes 15-16.]
    - (3 of 3), 1949; 1 box
    - 1947-1952 articles in Collier's, New York Times, and New York Herald, 1 box (2 volumes)